

Summary_

I am currently the Senior Data Scientist for Data Ventures, the commercial arm of New Zealand's national statistics agency (Statistics NZ). In this line of work I am responsible for the quality, methodology, and processing of large datasets such as telecommunications data, EFTPOS data, and banking data. As well as technical obligations, my role also has a heavy consultancy focus, whereby I am required to work closely with a variety of customers to understand their needs around data. Alongside my work, I am concurrently conducting a PhD in Psychology with a strong focus on structural equation modeling of longitudinal datasets. Through my combination of work and studies, I have a broad range of experience in advanced statistical methods and the ability to productionise my methods in a cloud environment. Previous to my current role, I focused on producing analytics with a large data warehouse containing linked person-level administrative data from Government called the Integrated Data Infrastructure (IDI).

Employment_

Statistics New Zealand	2019 - Present
SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST	
University of Otago	2019 - 2020
Assistant Research Fellow Te Runanga o Ngai Tahu	2018 - 2019
Statistician Statistics New Zealand	2016 - 2019
Statistical Analyst University of Otago	2013 - 2016
Senior Research Assistant Queensland Department of Natural Resources and Mines	2013 - 2015
Project Officer University of Otago	2012 - 2014
RESEARCH ASSISTANT	

Education

Victoria University of Wellington	Wellington
DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY	Present
University of Otago	Dunedin
MASTER OF SCIENCE	2016

Awards and scholarships ______

2018 IPANZ Young Professional Of The Year (Top 3)	Institute of Public	
	FAINZ TOUTING PTOTESSIONAL OF THE TEAT (TOP 5)	Administration NZ
2018	Victoria Doctoral Scholarship	Victoria University
		of Wellington
2015	Otago Research Master's Scholarship	University of Otago

Publications

- 1. Winter, T., Jose, P., Riordan, B., Bizumic, B., Ruffman, T., Hunter, J., & Scarf, D. (n.d.). Left-wing support of authoritarian submission to protect against societal threat. *Scientific Reports*.
- 2. Riordan, B., Winter, T., Flett, J., Scarf, D., Jose, P., & Conner, T. (n.d.). Does the fear of missing out (FoMO) moderate the relationship between social networking use and affect? A daily diary study. *Computers in Human Behavior*.
- 3. Winter, T., Riordan, B., Surace, A., Scarf, D., & Jose, P. (2020). A tutorial on the use of informative bayesian priors for minority research. *Preprint: PsyArXiv*.

- 4. Zimmerman, H., Riordan, B., Winter, T., Bartonicek, A., & Scarf, D. (n.d.). Are new zealand psychology students more susceptible to essentialist explanations for mental illness? Neuroessentialism and mental illness stigma in psychology and non-psychology students. *New Zealand Journal of Psychology*.
- 5. Winter, T., Scarf, D., Riordan, B., Hunter, J., Tustin, K., Gollop, M., Taylor, N., Kokaua, J., & Poulton, R. (n.d.). A longitudinal study of mental wellbeing in students that transition into PhD study. *Frontiers in Psychology*.
- 6. Winter, T., Conner, T., & Jose, P. (2021). Methodological and conceptual complexities of assessing relationships between single-occasion CRP inflammation and daily affect. *Brain, Behavior, and Immunity Health*.
- 7. Raubenheimer, J. E., Riordan, B. C., Merrill, J. E., Winter, T., Ward, R. M., Scarf, D., & Buckley, N. A. (2021). Hey google! Will new zealand vote to legalise cannabis? Using google trends data to predict the outcome of the 2020 new zealand cannabis referendum. *International Journal of Drug Policy*.
- 8. Winter, T., Riordan, B., Pakpour, A., Griffiths, M., Mason, A., Poulgrain, J., & Scarf, D. (2020). Evaluation of the english version of the fear of COVID-19 scale and its relationship with behavior change and political beliefs. *International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction*.
- 9. Riordan, B. C., Raubenheimer, J., Ward, R. M., Merrill, J. E., Winter, T., & Scarf, D. (2020). Monitoring the sentiment of cannabis-related tweets in the lead up to new zealands cannabis referendum. *Drug and Alcohol Review*.
- 10. Scarf, D., Zimmerman, H., Winter, T., Boden, H., Graham, S., Riordan, B. C., & Hunter, J. A. (2020). Association of viewing the films joker or terminator: Dark fate with prejudice toward individuals with mental illness. *JAMA Network Open*.
- 11. Graham, S., Mason, A., Riordan, B., Winter, T., & Scarf, D. (2020). Taking a break from social media improves wellbeing through sleep quality. *Cyberpsychology, Behavior, and Social Networking*.
- 12. Winter, T., Conner, T., & Jose, P. (2020). Identifying profiles of affective change: An ecological momentary assessment of flourishers. *Emotion*.
- 13. Trevis, K. J., McTavish, E., Winter, T., Fu, Y., McTavish, J., Wilson, B., Oliver, J., & Franz, E. A. (2019). Harnessing the brain's neuro-compensatory processes: Lessons from a high-functioning person with complete agenesis of the corpus callosum. *Neuropsychologie Clinique Et AppliquÃ*©e.
- 14. Winter, T., Riordan, B., & Surace, A. (2019). The relationship between hazardous alcohol use and discrimination among mÄ⊠ori in aotearoa new zealand. *Addiction*.
- 15. Surace, A., Riordan, B., & Winter, T. (2019). Do new zealand sexual minorities engage in more hazardous drinking than non-sexual minorities? *Drug and Alcohol Review*.
- 16. Pittar, N., Winter, T., Falland-Cheung, L., Tong, D., & Waddell, J. N. (2018). Scalp simulation a novel approach to site-specific biomechanical modeling of the skin. *Journal of the Mechanical Behavior of Biomedical Materials*.
- 17. Falland-Cheung, L., Waddell, J. N., Lazarjan, M. S., Jermy, M. C., Winter, T., Tong, D., & Brunton, P. A. (2017). Use of agar/glycerol and agar/glycerol/water as a translucent brain simulant for ballistic testing. *Journal of the Mechanical Behavior of Biomedical Materials*.
- 18. Franz, E. A., Fu, Y., Moore, M., Winter, T., Mayne, T., Debnath, R., & Stringer, C. (2016). Fooling the brain by mirroring the hand: Brain correlates of the perceptual capture of limb ownership. *Restorative Neurology and Neuroscience*.
- 19. Tong, D. C., Winter, T. J., Jin, J., Bennett, A. C., & Waddell, J. N. (2015). Quantification of subconcussive impact forces to the head using a forensic model. *Journal of Clinical Neuroscience*.
- 20. Winter, T. J., & Franz, E. A. (2014). Implication of the anterior commissure in the allocation of attention to action. *Frontiers in Psychology*.

Presentations and posters

Authoritarian submission on the left and right during the covid-19 pandemic in New Zealand

2020

New Zealand Psychological Society Conference, Wellington

Using overseas surveys to produce reliable models of sexual minorities

2019

New Zealand Population Conference, Wellington

Alcohol use disparities among gender and sexual minorities in New Zealand (Poster)	2019
Collaborative Perspectives on Addiction, Rhode Island Iwi data tool using integrated data and R Shiny	2017
Iwi Data Conference, Christchurch Using data to support a collective impact model of Maori potential	2016
Population Association of New Zealand Conference, Christchurch The effect of motherhood on income	2016
New Zealand Association of Economists conference, Wellington A machine learning approach to classifying life course outcomes	2016
Longitudinal and multivariate analysis network (Stats NZ), Wellington Methodology for comparing incomes between parents and non-parents	2016
Statistical methods seiminar (Stats NZ), Wellington Inter-hemispheric inhibition in the autistic brain	2014
Neuroethics seminar, Dunedin	

Skills_____

- Research design and analysis
- Structural equation modelling and causal analysis
- Bayesian statistics and multi-level modelling
- Machine learning techniques such as random forests and neural nets
- Cloud infrastructure experience via AWS
- Teaching reproducible research practices and statistics
- Health and Social psychology research
- Knowledge of Tikanga Māori